Hello everyone, I am Kaichao
大家好我是凯超
this course is about Rust ownership
本次课程内容是Rust所有权
the content includes
课程内容包括
introduction to the concepts and rules of ownership
所有权的概念和规则介绍
what is the transfer of ownership
所有权转移是什么
data copy and clone
数据copy和clone
function and ownership
函数与所有权
reference and borrow
引用reference和borrow
slice data type
slice数据类型
All computer programs need
所有的计算机程序都需要依赖
memory provided by the computer
计算机所提供的内存
Some languages such as Java, Go
一些语言比如Java, Go
use garbage collector to recycle
通过垃圾回收器来检测
unused memory
不再使用的内存
and release these memory
并且释放这些内存
Other languages like
其他语言比如
C and C++
C语言和C++
requires manual allocation and deallocation of memory
需要手动的分配和释放内存
Rust creatively invented a third way
Rust创造性的发明了第三种方式
through an ownership system and a set of rules
通过所有权系统和一系列规则
to manage memory
来管理内存
The compiler checks these rules during compilation
编译器在编译期间会检查这些规则
Since it is checked during compilation
由于是在编译期间检查
it doesn't slow down the execution of the program
所以并不会让程序的执行变慢
This is why Rust is considered as
这也是为什么说Rust
an efficient and safe programming language
是既高效又安全的编程语言
Since it is a relatively new concept
由于是比较新的概念
it may be difficult to understand at first
刚开始可能会比较难理解
But rest assured it's pretty simple
但是大家请放心它本身非常简单
as you write more Rust code
随着你写的Rust代码越来越多
get familiar with it
越来越熟悉
you will have better understanding about ownership
你会有更多的理解和体会
Ownership is the core feature that sets Rust apart from other languages
所有权是Rust区别其他语言最独特
最核心的特性
understanding ownership is extremely important when writing Rust code
理解所有权
是Rust编程极为重要的一个部分
The rules for Rust ownership include
Rust所有权的规则包括
each value in memory
内存里的任何值
has a variable corresponding to it
都有一个变量与之对应
called its owner
称之为它的owner
a value can only have one owner at a time
某一时刻
一个值只能有一个owner
the value will be dropped when the owner goes out of scope
当这个owner退出作用域后值会被丢弃
For the dropping process
那丢弃的过程是
the compiler will automatically call a function for us
编译器会帮我们自动调用一个函数
the function is named drop
叫做drop
to clean the value
进行丢弃
Here let's look at a code snippet
这里我们看一个代码片段
We define a variable s
我们定义了一个变量s
its data type is string
它的数据类型是string
and contains a string "hello"
保存着一个字符串是hello
When we define s
那我们在定义的时候
the corresponding memory space will be allocated
它会分配对应的存储空间
Before defining s
在定义s之前
s is not available
那s是不可用的
after defining s
在定义s之后
variable s is available
变量s都是可用的
When it meets the end of the curly brace
当遇到了大括号结尾的位置
s exits the scope
s就退出了作用域
the corresponding memory space will be released
释放对应的存储空间
When we assign a value to a variable
当我们对变量进行赋值时
something happened
会发生
the ownership gets transfered to a new owner, which is called move
所有权的转移也就是move
Let's look at another code snippet
我们来再看一个代码片段
here we define a variable, s1
这里我们定义了一个变量是s1
the type is string
它的类型是string
When define it, we will allocate space accordingly
在我们定义的时候会对应的分配存储
In the second line we copy s1 to s2
第二行我们将s1复制给s2
At the same time, the ownership of the value in s1 is transferred to s2
同时s1对应值的所有权也转移至s2
s1 gets invalid
那s1会失效
When s2 goes out of scope, the corresponding space for string will be released
当s2退出作用域时会释放对应的
字符串存储空间
For simple types such as number, boolean, char etc
如果是简单的类型比如数值，布尔
Char等等
assignment involves copying the data implicitly
赋值会隐式地发生数据的拷贝操作
instead of transferring ownership
而不是转移所有权
implicitly
它是通过隐式地
The compiler will call copy function implicitly
编译器会隐式的
调用一个copy函数
We just saw it
我们刚才看到了
We don't want the original variable gets invalid immediately after assignment
我们并不希望
我们并不希望在赋值时让原有的变量
We don't want the original variable gets invalid immediately after assignment
立即失效
by copy and clone the data
那我们可以通过数据的拷贝和克隆
that is, the copy and clone trait
也就是copy和clone这两个接口
each trait has a specific function
两个接口会对应的有两个函数
the copy function and the clone function
是copy函数和clone函数
use them to
使用它们可以
duplicate the same data withou transfer the ownership
不把
当前变量对应值的所有权进行转移
duplicate the same data withou transfer the ownership
而是复制一份新的数据
The copy interface works for almost
copy接口适用于基本上
all primitive types
所有的基本类型和由
and complex types made of primitive types
基本类型构成的复杂类型
such as u32, bool, char and tuples etc.
比如u32, bool, char
和tuples等等
For data types that implements the clone trait
clone接口, 实现clone的数据类型
when we call the function clone explicitly
当我们显示地调用
it will clone the same data on the heap
clone函数的时候会把数据
在堆上重新clone一份新的
Such data types include
这样的数据类型包括
string
字步串string
hashmap, vector, etc.
hashmap, vector等等
Now let's look at a simple example
现在我们来看一个简单的例子
We define a
我们定义了一个
string s1
字符串s1
at the same time, clone s1 and assign it to s2
同时将s1 clone并赋值给s2
When we print s1 s2, we can see
当我们打印s1 s2时候可以看到
both s1 and s2 are valid
s1 s2都是有效的
When we remove the clone function
当我们把clone函数去掉
re-run it
重新执行
we will get an error, s1 is no longer available
我们会发现抛出异常 s1已经不再可用
because its ownership has been transferred to s2
因为它的所有权已经转移至s2
Similarly, we can test the vector
同样的 我们可以测试一下vector
data type
数据类型
We define a variable x whose value is
我们定义了一个变量x 它对应的值是
vec![1,2]
assign x to y and transfer ownership
将x赋值给y 同时发生所有权的转移
when we print y, it's success
当我们打印y的时候是成功的
When we try to print x, we will find a compilation error
当我们尝试去打印x 会发现编译异常
because our x has no ownership anymore
因为我们的x已经不再具有所有权
This is a short comment on the code snippet we just talked about
这是对我们刚才
测试的代码片段一个简单注释
We allocate its space when defining s1
我们在定义s1的时候分配了它的存储
duplicate the same data from s1 to s2 via clone
通过clone将s1同样的数据克隆至s2
s1 is still valid
那s1同时还是有效的
When s1, s2 go out of the scope
当s1 s2作用域结束的时候
release their spaces respectively
分别释放自己对应的存储空间
we can use
我们可以通过
the keyword derive to
derive标签来
automatically implement copy or clone trait
自动的派生copy或者clone接口
generally, we do not need to implement the copy trait explicitly
我们一般也不需要显示的实现copy
an exception is for struct
一个例外情况是我们的结构体
if all of its fields are copyable
如果它所有的字段都是可以copy的
then we can use derive(copy) to implement the copy trait
那我们可以通过derive(copy)
then the struct is also copyable now
让我们结构体也
实现copy这样的一个功能
Clone is slower than copy
clone相比copy来说它会更慢
as it is duplicating all data
因为它是发生所有数据
的拷贝
on the heap
并且是在堆上
clone() cannot be omitted
clone函数的调用不可缺省
we need to call it explicitly
需要显示的给出来
Let's take a look at
接着我们来看一下
the relationship between function and ownership
函数与所有权的关系
Similar to assignment
和赋值很类似
passing a variable to a function also leads to
将某个变量传递给函数也会发生
the transfer of ownership
所有权的转移
or copy of the data
或者copy
if
如果是
if the data is copyable
如果是可以copy的数据类型的话
the copy function will be called implicitly
就会发生copy操作
A function's return value
函数可以通过返回值
can transfer ownship of a value
把函数内的变量
from inside function to outside of it
对应的值的所有权转移至函数外
Here we define a function takes_ownership
这里我们定义了一个函数是takes_ownership
it accepts a string
他接受一个string
the parameter name is some_string
参数名是some_string
it will take ownership of the value
他会获得值的所有权
Here we do a simple print operation
这里我们做一个简单打印操作
When the scope of some_string ends
当some_string作用域结束的时候会
the corresponding space will be released
释放对应的存储
In the main function
在main函数里面
we define a string s
我们定义了一个字符串s
pass s to the function takes_ownership
将s传递给takes_ownership
ownership transfer happens
这样一个函数并发生了所有权的转移
s is no longer available from now on
后面s就不再可用
Another function is makes_copy
另外一个函数是makes_copy
It is similar to takes_ownership
它和takes_ownership很类似
but its parameter is an integer
只不过它的参数是一个
只不过它的参数是一个整数类型
When our function finishes executing
当我们的函数执行完成之后
the parameter goes out of scope and is popped from the stack
我们的参数作用域结束会从栈上弹出
Here we define a variable x with value 5
这里我们定义了一个变量x 它的值是5
when we pass x to the makes_copy function
那我们将x传递给makes_copy函数时
what actually happens is copying the corresponding value of x
其实发生的是x对应值的拷贝
you can continue to use x after calling makes_copy
在makes_copy代码后边还可以继续使用x
Let's look at a scenario for returning value
我们再来看一个返回值的场景
Here we define a function that is
这里我们定义了一个函数是
gives_ownership
it returns a string
它返回了一个string
inside the function
在函数内
we define a string some_string
我们定义了一个字符串some_string
and allocate a certain amount of memory space automatically
并分配了一定的存储空间
some_string is returned
我们将some_string返回
and its ownership gets transferred out of the function
并将所有权转移至函数外
so that at the end of our function it won't
这样在我们函数结束时不会去
free up the corresponding space
释放对应的存储空间
In the main function, let's calling gives_ownership
在main函数里面我们调用gives_ownership
assign its return value to the s1 variable
将返回值赋给s1变量
then s1 gets the ownership of the new string
那s1就获得了
新的字符串存储空间的所有权
Another function we defined is takes_and_gives_back
我们定义的另外一个函数是takes_and_gives_back
It takes a string and returns a string
他接收一个字符串并返回一个字符串
Since a_string is returned
由于我们会把a_string返回
the ownership will be transferred to outside of the function
所以所有权会转移至函数外
That is, at the end of the function, it will not
也就是在函数结束的时候并不会
release the space which is used to store the string
进行销毁存储空间
Here we define a string s2
这里我们定义了一个字符串s2
and pass s2 to the function takes_and_gives_back
并且将s2传递给函数takes_and_gives_back
函数
the ownership of value in s2 is transferred to the function
发生了s2对应值的所有权转移
the return value of the function is assigned to s3
并将函数返回值的结果赋值给s3
thereby transferring the ownership of the return value to s3
从而将函数返回值的所有权转移至s3
From now on, s3 is available and s2 is no longer available
后面的话 s3是可用的 s2不再可用
when reach the end of the main function
到达main函数的末尾的时候
s3 out of scope
s3退出作用域
realease the memory space occupied by the string
释放对应的存储空间
Next let's look at references and borrowing
接下来我们看一下引用和借用
In many cases we just want to use the value
在很多时候我们只是需要使用某个值
but don't want to take the ownership of the value
但并不希望去获取值所对应的所有权
to manage memory space
去管理内存空间
That can be achieved by references
那可以通过引用来实现
By prepending the varable name with a & symbol
我们通过在变量名前放置一个
& 符号
we then get a reference to the value
获取值的引用
When the parameter of a function is a reference
当函数的参数是引用时
we call it borrow
我们称之为borrow
References are immutable by default
也就是借用
引用默认是不可变的
mutable references need to be indicated with &mut
可变的引用是需要显示的指定
&mut, which is the abbreviation of mutable
通过&mut 也就是mutable的缩写来指定
Immutable reference means
不可变引用是指
the reference cannot change the value that it referred to
这个引用不能改变所对应的值
while mutable reference means
而可变引用指的是
the reference can make changes to the value that it referred to
该引用可以对值的内容进行改变
Scope of reference
引用的作用域
is different from the scope of variable
和变量的作用域不同
it's not at the end of the curly braces
它并不是在大括号的末尾
instead, its ending scope is at the last used place
而是在引用最后使用到的地方
进行结束
Here let's look at an example
这里我们来看一个例子
We define a function called calculate_length
我们定义了一个函数叫做calculate_length
it accepts a parameter that is a reference of string
他接受一个参数是string类型的引用
then returns an integer
然后返回一个整数
It calculates the length of the string
我们通过计算字符串的长度
and return
并且返回
when s goes out of scope
那s退出作用域
since it is a reference
由于它是引用
it will not release the space that it referred to
它并不会去清空对应的存储空间
In the main function
在main函数里面
we define a string s1 and allocate space for it
我们定义了字符串s1并分配了存储
then call calculate_length
我们调用calculate_length这样一个函数
borrow the value of the s1 variable
借用s1变量对应的值
then print s1 and the string length
然后打印我们的s1和
字符串长度
You can see that s1 is still available
可以看到s1依然是可用的
because calculate_length just
因为我们上面calculate_length只是对
borrows the value of s1
值的一个借用
ownership is not transferred
并没有去转移所有权
Next, let's look at an example of a mutable reference
接着我们来看一个可变引用的例子
We define a function called change
我们定义了一个函数是change
It takes a parameter some_string
它接受一个参数some_string
its type is a mutable reference to string
它的类型是一个string的可变引用
In the function
我们在函数内对我们
we did some operations on the referenced value
引用的值进行一系列操作
modify the value
修改值的内容
when the function is executed
当函数执行完成之后
the parameter some_string goes out of scope
参数some_string退出作用域
since it is a reference
由于它是引用
the space that it referred to won't get released
所以也不去清空存储空间
Let's define a variable s in the main function
我们在main函数里面定义了一个变量s
it is mutable and string type
是一个可变的string类型
Then call the function change
我们通过调用
change函数
with a mutable reference to the string
并且显示的
创建了可变引用 传递给我们的函数
When print s again
当我们再次打印的时候
it should output a new string
应该会输出一个新的字符串的结果
Next, let's look at the slice type
接下来我们来看一下slice类型
slice is used to refer to part of the continuous data in a collection
slice用于引用集合内的部分连续数据
it can be recognized as a data slice
可以看作是数据切片
Similar to reference
它和引用
it does not have the ownership of the value
很类似 也不拥有值所对应的所有权
The advantage of using slice is that it is bind to the value
使用slice好处是它会与
值进行绑定 退出作用域时
when value goes out of scope
the allocated space gets released
存储空间进行清空
and the slice will also be invalid at the same time
slice也同时会失效
The way to define a slice is through the & symbol
定义slice的方式是通过 &符号 变量名
given start and end positions
给定初始位置和结束位置
the end position is not included
end所对应的结束位置是不包含的
When the start position is 0
同时当开始位置是0的时候
it can be omitted
我们可以缺省
When the end position is the maximum length of our collection
结束位置是集合最大长度时
end can be omitted
end也可以缺省
When you need to reference the entire collection, both start and end can be omitted
需要引用整个集合时可以把start, end
同时缺省
Let's look at type signature of slice
slice类型签名如
for string slice
对于string slice
looks like this "&str"
是这样的一个符号 &str
for vector and array slice, it's &[T]
对于vector和array slice是这样的一个符号 &[T]
Let's look at an example of slice
我们来看一下slice定义的例子
We define a string "hello world"
我们定义了一个字符串 "hello world"
assign it to the s variable
把它赋值给s变量
We create a string slice
我们创建了一个string slice
it starts from 0 and ends at 5
它引用的位置是从0开始到5结束
does not include 5
不包含5
assign it to the variable hello
赋值给hello变量
Similarly let's define another string slice
同理 我们定义了另外一个string slice
it refers to the positions from 6 to 11
它引用的位置是从6到11
does not include 11 and is assigned to the variable world
不包含11 并赋值给world变量
Another example is
另外一个例子是
we create a slice of array
我们对数组创建了一个slice
referred to positions from 1 to 3
我们引用的是 位置1开始到3结束
does not include 3
不包含3
Its content is actually
它的内容其实就是
2 and 3 in this array
这个数组里面的2和3
Let's write an example together
接着我们来一起写一个例子
Here we define a function called first_word
这里我们定义了一个函数叫做first_word
It takes a string slice
它接收一个string slice
returns a string slice
返回一个string slice
First
首先
it will convert the string slice into a collection of bytes
它会将string slice转变成一个字节集合
call iter() of the collection
对字节集合调用iterator
returns an iterator
返回一个迭代器
then call enumerate()
并且调用enumerate
to get the position of each element
拿到对应的一个元素的位置
You can get the details of these functions
具体两个函数的详细内容可以
in Rust document
参考对应的引用文档
Then let's iterate over the elements
那当我们迭代的元素
when it is the bytecode of a space
它是一个空格所对应的字节码时
return a string slice
我们返回一个string slice
it starts at position 0
它的开始位置是0
end at the position of blank space
结束位置是我们空格
but does not include the space
对应的这样一个位置
但是不包含空格
When finishing the loop
当我们循环完之后
if no such blank space was found
没有找到这样的一个空格
we will just return the whole string as a slice
我们就返回完整的string slice
In the main function
我们在main函数里面去定义
let's define a string variable
一个string变量
call the first_word function to get the first word
我们调用first_word函数来计算第一个单词
print the word, and run
我们打印这样一个单词, 运行
We can see that the result is
可以看到我们的结果是
"hello"
第一个单词hello
So how does Rust ensure memory safety?
那么Rust是怎样保证内存安全性呢
thanks to ownership and reference
其实就是通过所有权和引用
When variable that has ownership goes out of scope
拥有所有权的变量在退出作用域时
it will automatically release the memory space
会自动清空值的内存空间
We have just mentioned that the compiler will
我们刚才已经提到了
automatically call drop function
编译器
会自动帮我们调用一个drop函数
to free up the memory
将存储空间给释放掉
And, there can only be one mutable reference
并且在同一时间最多只能有一个可变引用
or multiple immutable references at a time
或者是多个不可变引用
That is to say
也就是说
there can't be
不能同时存在
two or more mutable references at the same time
两个及两个以上的可变引用
because this would cause data conflicts
因为这样会产生数据冲突
since we can't tell
我们不清楚
which mutable reference is modifying the value
哪一个可变引用在修改值
and there can't be mutable and immutable refrences at the same time
并且也不能同时存在
可变引用和不可变引用
Because when we use immutable references
因为我们在使用不可变引用的时候
the assumption is that the value is unchanged
假设的就是 值是固定不变的
if there is a mutable reference at this time
如果这个时候存在了一个可变引用
then we can't tell
那我们并不清楚
if the value is changed by the mutable reference
这个值是不是已经被改变了
The compiler does not allow the exist of null pointers
编译器不允许空指针的存在
When referencing a piece of memory that has been dropped
当你
引用了一个已经被释放的内存的时候
compilation errors will be raised
会直接报编译错误
Referencing a portion of a value through slice
通过slice引用值的一部分
The memory life cycle of the value and
将值的内存生命周期和
the slice is bound together
slice的作用域绑定起来
so that there will be no abnormal situations like null pointers for reference
从而不会出现引用的异常情况
This is the end of today's class, thank you all
今天的课程到这里就结束了谢谢大家